<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pax vobis or a charme for tumultuous spirits. Being an earnest and Christian advice unto the people of London, to forbeare their disorderly meetings at VVestminster, least they prove to the disturbance of the great businesse in hand, pressed by divers waighty and considerable reasons offered to their serious thoughts. Together with a motion for the speedy reliefe of the poore distressed Protestants in Ireland : and for a publike fast that we may all joyne in harty supplications to God for them. / By Thomas Warmstry Minister of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E180_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12759</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859335</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159507</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159507)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 31:E180[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pax vobis or a charme for tumultuous spirits. Being an earnest and Christian advice unto the people of London, to forbeare their disorderly meetings at VVestminster, least they prove to the disturbance of the great businesse in hand, pressed by divers waighty and considerable reasons offered to their serious thoughts. Together with a motion for the speedy reliefe of the poore distressed Protestants in Ireland : and for a publike fast that we may all joyne in harty supplications to God for them. / By Thomas Warmstry Minister of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Thompson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christians --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159507:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159507:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PAX VOBIS OR A CHARME FOR tumultuous Spirits.</p>
            <p>Being an earneſt and Chriſtian advice unto the people of <hi>London,</hi> to forbeare their diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly meetings at <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> leaſt they prove to the diſturbance of the great buſineſſe in hand, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by divers waighty and conſiderable reaſons offered to their ſerious thoughts.</p>
            <p>Together with a motion for the ſpeedy reliefe of the poore diſtreſſed Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland:</hi> and for a publike faſt that we may all joyne in harty ſupplications to God for them.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS WARMSTRY Miniſter of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>Study to be quiet, and to doe your owne buſineſſe. <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Theſſ. 4.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Thompſon,</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:159507:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159507:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PAX VOBIS,</hi> OR A Charme for tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous Spirits.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being an earneſt and Chriſtian ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice unto the people of <hi>London,</hi> to forbeare their diſorderly meetings at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat workes if they end happily, are great Bleſſings for the moſt part, if unhappily they diſolve into great Curſes or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes. If they goe up orderly, and ſtand firmely, they may yeeld ſhelter and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance unto many. If they faile or miſcarry, they doe not onely breake themſelves to peeces with their weight, but doe alſo cruſh and grind thoſe, that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ruine, who expecting a ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lter, meete with a confuſion.</p>
            <p>The worke which is now in hand in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I may truely ſay it is a great worke, and that in various and diverſe reſpects: great it is, if wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the body that ſways it, the very poize whereof
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159507:3"/>muſt needes be active, and can hardly leave any light impreſſions. The very name and ſound of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gives gravity and weight unto the aire, me thinks that carries it, and hath a kind of reſt and ſollid ſtay upon the eare more then other voyces that are uſually of a fluid and waſting condition, and whoſe very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is a conſumption: And if the name bee ſo ponderous, what is the body it ſelfe thinke you? The leaſt graines in the compoſition whereof, outwaigh whole pounds in other Corporations. Great it is in reſpect of the ſubject they have to worke upon, being the vaſt and large Fabricke of more then one ſtate and Church. Great it is in regard of their ſcope and aime, which extends it ſelfe through the whole Horizon, both of pollicie and religion, and hath in its view and proſpect, all that concernes either the Temporall or ſpirituall good of many Millions &amp; Myriads of people, who muſt either ſtand or fall by the ſucceſſe or miſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of their actions. And great it is too in Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe many and great difficulties they are to encounter in the procuring of that good iſſue they aime at.</p>
            <p>So that there is indeede a great accumulation of greatneſſe in that buſineſſe which is now in hand, and is likely to give over and conclude either in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding happineſſe, or exceſſive miſery, eſpecially as the caſe now ſtands with us, wee can hardly find roome for any meane expectation.</p>
            <p>And therfore it muſt needes very highly concerne us all to deſire, and endavour in what wee may, that it may proceede orderly and ſucceede proſperouſly, and to remove all ſhelfes and rockes of impediments which this royall veſſell or navie may ſplit upon unto our generall ſhipwracke.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159507:3"/>
            <p>This deſire I hope is ſetled in all that are not of a a meere Diabolicall ſpirit, but the effects thereof are various, and unlike, and not alwayes anſwerable unto the united intentions, but to the variety of mens judgements, and Fancies, in the deſignation of thoſe meanes which they diverſly conceive to be moſtapt, and proper for the compaſſing of thoſe generall aymes wherein all perhaps agree: The errours whereof are alwayes diffuſive of themſelves into thoſe deſignes or motions which proceed from them; and indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many and various apprehenſions, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, that have ſhewed themſelves buſie in the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the worke, I cannot but conclude ſome to be miſtaken, ſince I finde them lying ſo farre aſſnnder from one another, that they cannot move in any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect lines unto the ſame center or purpoſe.</p>
            <p>There are (if I misjudge not) but foure generall miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes which doe alwayes (though not alwayes equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (ſhare and divide betwixt them the miſconduct of all enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>The firſt and moſt malignant is the errour in the end, when the worke is guided to a wrong purpoſe, when the very goale or marke it ſelf is miſtaken: which whereſoever it is found, doth uſually pervert the whole courſe of the action, ſo that it becomes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely wild and ſavage: Such kind of wandrings being like unto the errours, and failings of the firſt concoction in the body, which are obſerved (I take it) by Phiſitions to be incorrigble by any after worke that nature can performe. Since the propoſall of the right end is the great Scale, or ſtandard where by all the parts and couducts of the buſineſſe muſt be meaſured and waighed, add he that meaſures with a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159507:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159507:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:159507:5"/>crooked rule, is not like to make ſtraight worke, if the ſcales be not even, how ſhall a man know the waight of that, which is put into them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond generall Errour is the miſchoice of the due way or meanes: when men ſet up the right marke before themſelves, but for want of a good ayme doe not guide the ſhaft in the right line. They meane to ſett up at a good Towne, but they doe not take the right way over to get thither. And this though it be not in all reſpects ſo curſed as the former, that having the allay of a good intention, yet if we may judge of thinges by the Event, as it may ſeeme more miſerable ſince there is ſome good loſt in a ſort therein, which is not in the other, as is miſcarriage of a pious intent, ſo it proves many times within few degrees, if not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as pernitious.</p>
            <p>The third ſort of Errours or failings whereby great and good deſignes are baned, is the want of due force or ſtrength in the motion, when the enterpriſe langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth and dyeth in the way for want of ſpirit to carry it through unto the Butt, and though the Arrow be well guided, yet it falls ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt of the marke, and ſo fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſhort of the victory and prize.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt is the want of a right gage, or moderation, when there is too much force or impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe in the ſetting forward of the buſineſſe, ſo that like a Charret that is driven too furiouſly, it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturned with its owne ſpeede. Or as a Bowle that is well weighed, and biaſt, but is at home before its time, and ſo over-runnes the Miſtris: And the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of theſe foure errours is the work of the foure Cardinall virtues, Iuſtice, Prudence, Fortitude, and Temporance. Iuſtice gives us a true meaning, ſets us
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159507:5"/>upon the right end, Prudence directs us to the choyce of the right meanes, Fortitude keepes us from lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing in the motion, Temperance from exceeding or overturning it.</p>
            <p>For the two former of theſe errors as concerneth the great worke in hand, I hope there neede bee no agues or ſhiverings in the States for them, or at leaſt if there bee any ground for our feares therein, I hope God will be the Phyſitian: we have had I hope many good experiences both of the integrity and wiſedome of the Parliament, that may keepe us from being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carefull for preventing miſtakes either in the end, or the meanes: Their uprightneſſe I hope will fixe them ſteady upon the one, and their prudence guide them in the other: yet I wiſh they may remember too that they are men, and there are clowdes of corruption which may produce evill, or hinder good, even in the greateſt concurrence of the the beſt and wiſeſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, if God be not moderatour of their workes, and therefore even in this, our joynt dependance muſt be upon him. Since it is the generall valuation that our praved natures have ſet upon us, and which the ſpirit of God hath truely taken of us, and recorded in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writ, that the children of men are deceitfull upon the waights.</p>
            <p>For the third, there is onely one thing, in which I could willingly preſſe for ſpeed, if I might be heard, becauſe every moments delay, may be paid for too dearely, with the loſſe of Chriſtian blood, and that is in the deſigne for the releife of <hi>Ireland.</hi> It was the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Poet, that <hi>nulla unquam de morte hominis, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statio longa eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159507:6"/>
            <p>But I may ſay as truely herewith a lettle alteration <hi>nulla unquam de morte hominis cunctatio parva eſt;</hi> where the ſlownes of the proceedings leaveth mens lines un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſpoyle, There every little deferring is too much. Mee thinkes when that poore Church and Kingdome lyesa bleeding to death, and every minute may give ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage unto the fury of the adverſary, conſultaion had not need too take up to much of the time, leaſt the opportunity of action, and application may be loſt in it. Too much caution is no part of wiſedome, where neceſſity is urgent for a ſpeedy redreſſe, and in this caſe wee had all need to be ſpeedy and earneſt in this matter, every one of us in our prayers and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto God; when the fire of Gods wrath was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out upon the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> It was no time for <hi>Aaron</hi> to dally, he muſt goe in all haſt: See how <hi>Moſes</hi> poſts him forward <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.46. <hi>Take the cenſer, and put fire therein of the Altar and put therein Incenſe, and goe quickly unto the congregation, and make an Attonement for them, for there is wrath gone out from the Lord.</hi> One fire muſt quench another, the fire of the Altar, even of new devotion the fire of Gods wrath is judgement, and affliction, and truely a ſpeedy devotion ſhould ſet us all upon an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and earneſt interceſſion to God for the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thole diſtreſſed people, from the rage and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their adverſaries. To the furtherance whereof if the King and Parliament, would be pleaſed to enjoyne a publique Faſt amongſt us for that purpoſe, it might have a good ſavour in it of Chriſtian compaſſion, and might by Gods grace be a praevalent meanes to draw downe the ſhowers of his heavenly mercy, to quench the flames of that Tyranny, and inhumane cruelty in which our poore Brethren there, are ſchorched, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159507:6"/>conſumed. But yet the haſt muſt not be onely in this, while <hi>Moſes</hi> prayeth, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> muſt fight too, there is great neede of a timely reliefe, even in outward ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours and ſupplyes, leaſt our idle devotion render our Prayers like unto that fruitleſſe Charity of which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, that dwelt onely in the tongue and had nothing of the hand, could ſay, depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled, but afforded nothing. I wiſh therefore God may put it into our hearts to ſecond our prayers with a voluntary contribution, which would be an exceptable ſacrifice to God.</p>
            <p>And that the Parliament would thinke of a ſpeedy courſe to ſend them ſupplies. and truely I am glad you made this a part of your late Petition to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and I hartily wiſh it may take with them ſo, that they may conſider of it in time, leaſt their blood cry againſt us for our ſlowneſſe in relieving, as well as againſt them for their fury in deſtroying. Our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may perhaps be as offenſive to God, as the rage of the Adverſary. It is no time to ſtand diſcuſſing of niceties: to ſtand upon ceremonies and formalities, when a whole Church and Kingdome is under a deſperate diſeaſe; eſpecially when every delay makes the evill the more remedileſſe: In ſuch a caſe we ſhould deale as a Phyſitian adviſeth, (if my memory faile not) <hi>In morbis Aſtralibus,</hi> in Appoplexies and ſuch like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate and ſudden diſtempers, not ſtand too much upon Election, and Compoſition, but apply that which is next at hand, ſo it bee proper for the diſeaſe. Oh take heede I beſeech you of the curſe of <hi>Meroz,</hi> and remember that ſaying of the wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.11.12. <hi>If thou forbeare to deliver them, that are drawne unto death, and thoſe that are ready to bee ſlaine, if thou ſayest,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159507:7"/>Behold we know it not, doth not hee, that pondreth the heart conſider it, and hee that keepeth thy ſoule, doth not hee know it? and ſhall not hee render to every man according to his worke?</hi> I confeſſe I would beg on my knees for ſpeede here: a holy raſhneſſe in this caſe would be more tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then to be overwſe in deliberation. But for other matters, I hope their ſoftneſſe is for ſafety. Since for ought I know, they may not onely admitt of a conſiderate proceeding, but receive it. And though the current of the buſineſſe may bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſlower, then perhaps the too ſpeedy expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſome that doe not ſo well conſider the greatnes of the body, which commonly moves more ſlowly, if not leſſe ſecurely, the weight of the burthen and the buſineſſe that they have upon them, which may well forbid them to make uſe of their wings: or the great intricacy and perplexity, together with the many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties unto which it is expoſed. Yet I hope in the end, they may beare that Motto, <hi>Sat citò, Si ſat benè,</hi> And that it will appeare to have beene not delay, but deliberation: And to have proceeded not from any dulneſſe in the body, or from any coldneſſe or indeffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency in the proſecution of thoſe happie ends, which the preſent neceſſity of Church and State preſents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their wiſedomes, but rather from a ſerious and watchfull care to bring accounts and opportunities together, and to avoyd precipitancy, and prevent the halfe vertue of repentance, which divides it ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Glory and Ignominie in the worke: yet it is my prayer, and therefore my hope, that this Procaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of theirs, if wee bee not too impatient, may prove like the contagion of <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of whoſe proceedings was the ſpeed of his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159507:7"/>and that it may <hi>Restituere rem,</hi> for ſo it is ſaid of him by the <hi>Romane</hi> Orator, <hi>unus homo nobis cunctando reſtituit rem.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ponebat enim rumores ante ſalutem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo poſtque magiſque viri nunc Gloria claret,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Give me leave to tranſlate it thus:</l>
               <l>One good man did to us reſtore</l>
               <l>The Commonwealth, neere leſt before</l>
               <l>By wiſe delay, not taking care</l>
               <l>Of every Rumour, he did heare</l>
               <l>But in his heart preferring ſtill</l>
               <l>The peoples ſafty, not their will,</l>
               <l>His name then glorious well may be</l>
               <l>With us, and with poſteritie.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And as it was with him, ſo I truſt we ſhall all have good cauſe to tranſlate this Elegy unto this great body If God pleaſe to compact the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo that they may be <hi>Vnus homo,</hi> as he was united, in their Iudgements and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and preferre not tumultuous rumours and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before that which is good and healthfull to Church and State. I truſt then the delay will be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recompenſed in the happie ſucceſſe, and crowned concluſion, that it will appeare not to have beene a putting off of the buſineſſe, but a prevention of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity, which ſome men oft times more worke to undoe, then they had to doe in the beginning, and Caſts them backe by their ſpeede more then the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſoftneſſe of their motion could have done.</p>
            <p>They that ride too far in a day, having a great Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to goe, come many times ſhort of their Iournies end.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:159507:8"/>
            <p>An aftergame is but the ſecond part of wiſedome, and proves many times full of difficulty and hazard, and therefore the ſafeſt way is, to take time and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, when wee may have it, to play the fore game well, leaſt our negligent ſpeede leave us to remedileſſe errors, or at leaſt not corrigible without ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit.</p>
            <p>And truely the Stake is here ſo great, and every one of us ſo much a ſharer in it, as comprehending Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Peace, Honour and proſperity of the whole Church and State, that wee have all great reaſon to give them leave, whom we have truſted to play it for us, to thinke well upon their caſts, leaſt ſome overſight might end it too ſoone to all our undoing, and wee ſhould have occaſion to wiſh it were rather not yet begunne then ended. The perills are ſo many and great, that they had neede looke round about them every ſteppe, leaſt if the feet ſhould outrun the eyes, the haſt ſhould leave the ſpeede behind it, and like <hi>Mephiboſheths</hi> nurſe let the whole buſineſſe fall and lame it. The danger I conceive lies not in this then, but rather in our impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, leaſt when wee think them too ſlow, wee ſhould enforce them to too much haſt in their progreſſe; and through a deſire that they ſhould goe on, hinder them from going right, and whilſt wee require ſatiſ faction for our importunity, we looſe the expected en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of our felicity; which is the laſt errour, for prevention whereof. I am bold (my brethren) eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to addreſſe my ſelfe unto you at this time, and to beſeech you in the name of God, and for the mercies of Chriſt Ieſus, that you would not by any unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able preſſures, or Tumultuous ſollicitations of the buſineſſe in hand, attempt the diſturbance of this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159507:8"/>happie conjuncture, but that it may bee permitted to glide on ſmoothly and calmely and peaceably, as is moſt correſpondent unto thoſe peaceable ends, which they drive at, not inturrupting that great aſſembly, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by any uncivill or diſtempered concourſes, or by any rude or immodeſt clamours; and that for theſe reaſons, which I ſhall here preſent unto you, drawne firſt from the conſideration of the nature of the buſineſſe; ſecondly, from the different conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſelves and that great body, and of the different intent, that is betwixt you in the matter; Thirdly, from the great and generall concernement, not onely of your ſelves, but of the whole Church and Kingdome, That I ſay not of Chriſtendome and the whole world therein; Fourthly, from the great impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and intollerable prejudices that ſuch procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of yours may ſeem to lay upon the Parliament. Fiftly, from the great impediments and diſtractions that you may create unto the carriage of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, from the great derogation that this may cauſe both in our owne and after times, from the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of thoſe good Lawes, which they ſhall now make, and the too too ſemblable excuſes, that you may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ill minded people withall, to a colourable under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing thereof, and a ſubſtraction of obedience from them.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The nature of the worke, which is a worke of of peace and righteouſnes, requires a peaceable and calme proceeding, for though wee haue found it true through Gods miraculous mercy ſometime, that union hath beene rayſed out of the aſhes that Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult and diviſion have left; Yet ſuch peace is a rare
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159507:9"/>
               <hi>Phaenix</hi> and ſuch extraordinary reuolution are noe proper ſcales for us to meaſure our proceedings by. Rules and actions muſt bee collected from thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, which are daily and frequent, not from wonders, and miracles, which are ſeldome ſeene. Surgeons thinke it not ſafe to ſtabb theire patients, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one perhaps was ſo deliuered of an impoſtume. The prouidence of God, that overſwayeth all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, can turne the deſigne of an enemy into the worke of a phiſition. And he that made all things of nothing, can make what hee pleaſeth of any thing, and bringe his owne moſt wiſe concluſions, out of the moſt contradictory premiſes. But yet thoſe rare and ſtupendious workes of his, are noe warrant for us to preſcribe to him ſtill to bring to paſſe ſuch ſtrang converſions.</p>
            <p>Secondly; as it is a worke of righteouſnes, directed to the abolliſhing of thoſe errors and vices, which through the mallice of the Deuill and his iuſtruments are of late crept into the Church; ſo it abhors tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, and uiolence.</p>
            <p>The fruit of righteouſnes is ſowne in peace of them, that make peace; ſaith the Spirit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and peace. And if wee ſurvay the proceedings of thoſe Miniſters and happy Inſtruments both of peace and righteouſneſſe, the Apoſtles and Deſciples of Chriſt Ieſus, which are good patternes for us to walke by, wee ſhall finde that though they had at leaſt as many difficulties to meete with, as the ſumme of all thoſe wee can obſerve or imagine can make up to lie againſt the buſineſſe in hand, yet they made uſe of noe tumultuous, or uiolent practiſes for the compaſſing of theire ends, no-diſtempered or uncivill
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159507:9"/>clamours, no threatning demeanours, noe contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous carriage againſt Governours. Though they found them too untractable, and farre from admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of that enterptize they entended. They encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred indeed with much violence, and ſedition, many confluences, and erruptions of the people, they had to doe with, breaking out upon them like violent ſtormes, or the unrully ſurges of the enraged Ocean. All you may ſee in the Acts of the holy Apoſtles, but for themſelves they raiſed none, but leading on the work with a Calme ſtreame, and with a peaceable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate zeale prevailed ſo farre as to beate downe before them the unrully oppoſitions they found in their way. And make it appeare unto the wonder of the world, that God ſaveth not by ſword or ſpeare, but by a ſecret and almoſt unperceived operation, and that the ſoft and ſtill voice wherein God was, was more powerfull then the moſt violent winds, Then the moſt teareing thunder, yea then the moſt enraged flames, that any humane fury could kindle or raiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. Neither did they abſtaine as ſome may perhaps object either for want of oppoſition, or through any defect of Chriſtian zeale, or of a party to countenance a Tumult: Oppoſition they had enough to provoke them as is well knowne, and wee have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared their zeale! Alas yours at the hotteſt, if wee ſpeake of pious zeale, is but a ſparke unto their flame; you may and do (I doubt) exceed in intemperate heartes: But divine zeale, it is a benigne flame, ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with humility, and charity, that a Feaver, a diſeaſe, this a healthfull vigour of the Soule, and in this I dare be bold to ſay, they were as farre beyond the beſt of you, as the Sunne at noone beyond an <hi>Ignis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:159507:10"/>neither wanted they a party to have ſhewed themſelves in the matter, with as much noiſe and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence if they had pleaſed, as you have done, If you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider either number or unity, as you may ſee if you look upon thoſe great and miraculous increments, and numerous collonies, that tranſplanted themſelves at once into the Church, even by about three thouſands at a time, as you may read in the acts of the Apoſtles, for their number, and if you looke upon that one minde, and one heart which was in them, which could not but adde much ſttength unto their multitude, ſo that their forbearance was not out of any ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, but out of a carefull watchfulneſſe, not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the <hi>Decorum</hi> of a Chriſtian moderation, and to doe Chriſts worke according to his owne rule and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, in whom the ſtrength of the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> was joyned with the meekneſſe, and patience of a Lambe, and the wiſedome of the ſerpent, with the ſimplicity of the Dove. And ſurely beloved if we would walke in their ſtepps, it might be a good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our attaining to the like ends, Since we (if our ſinnes have not altered the caſe) have the ſame God, and patron, of the ſame power and mercy, to protect the ſame cauſe that they had. And if our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have deprived us of him, it is not all the violence wee can uſe, nor the moſt impatient ſollicitation we can ſet upon, that can purchaſe any bleſſing to the matter in hand. Therefore in this reſpect, my advice is unto you, and I hope I ſhall joyne with you, to turne your violence in that kind you wot of, to an holy vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon God in your prayers, and inſtant ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Throne of grace, that with united for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſanctified importunities you would aſſault the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159507:10"/>Allmighty, for his mercy and compaſſion, <hi>quaſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> facta,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaketh as an united party, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Chriſtians in your holy aſſemblies; and this as hee ſpeaketh would be <hi>vis Deo grata,</hi> a force very accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in deed unto the Lord, but for your Tumultuous aſſemblies, I know no ſuch warrant to judge them plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant unto him, ſince I ſee not any Commiſſion you have from God unto that purpoſe; nor any good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion that they beare unto that iſſue, which wee ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly hope to be happy in.</p>
            <p>Adde unto this, that it is a worke of Medicine, or healing, not of deſtruction, or diſſolution, but ſo far onely as our preſent tumours and Corruptions make neceſſary unto that, the whole ſtate is that great body to be Phiſickt, and cured. The civill State or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth in the outward, and pollitique conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the outward part or Fabrique, the Church in the ſpirituall conſideration, may well be taken for the inwards, or bowells, or if you will, the Soule of that body. For theſe two make up but one and the ſame, and differ no futher then the extemall parts or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from the inward or ſpirituall part of one, and the ſame man. And as the outward parts are for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the body for the ſoule, ſo the outward ſtate of the Common-wealth, is for the Church or ſpiritual part; and as the cure and managing of the body, is to be directed principally to the good of the ſoule, ſo the affaires and carriages of the Civill ſtate, to be directed principally to the preſervation of the State ſpirituall, in a Chriſtian Common wealth, which is the only living body of this kind; Heathen ſtates being at the beſt but dead Carcaſes, void of all inward life as it were. And therefore theſe two muſt not be ſeparated too farre,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159507:11"/>but joyntly cared for, with a principall regard ever had unto the ſpirituall ends, ſince the greatneſſe or flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of the Common-wealth is onely ſo farre true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfortable, and healthfull, as it tends to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of Religion, and ſervice the of God, which is the healthfull conſtitution of the Church. And therefore thoſe Polititians, or Stateſmen that make Religion, and the Church but a meanes unto outward ends, they ſet the Cart before the Horſe, and are prepoſterous in their deſignes.</p>
            <p>The union betwixt theſe two is like the union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the body and the ſoule, which is the uery defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of life, the ſeparation, if to tall, is death, and what ever tends thereto, leads unto a diſſolution. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſoever divides theſe two too farre and makes them of too different a conſideration, goes about to divide the forme from the matter.</p>
            <p>For as <hi>Anima</hi> is <hi>tota in toto,</hi> ſo I dare bee bould to ſay, the Church is extended, or at leaſt ſhould bee through all the members of a Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: ſo that even the ſtate is an Ecleſiaſticall body. Some concluſions wil follow upon this, that might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps diſcover ſome Paralogiſmes in the ordinary diſcourſe of theſe times, but I purſue the buſineſſe I have in hand.</p>
            <p>The diſtempers of the Church are like thoſe extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and diſorders, which are in the faculties or paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſoule. The ſores of the Common-wealth as the wounds of the body. And as in the humane or naturall, theſe two have a mutual, coaction or reaction; the diſtemper of the ſoule cauſing diſeaſes in the body and on the Contrary the diſeaſes of the body procur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inordinate affections in the ſoule. So here, the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159507:11"/>in the Church are the cauſes of the miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in the Common-wealth, and the diſtempers of the Common-wealth bring forth diſeaſes of the Church, And to ſpeake truely I doe more then doubt, that for the preſent wee are vnder a ſhrewd Complication of theſe two kinds of diseaſes: therefore it is time to looke after the Phiſitian, and who is that? it will bee worth the knowing.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Archiatros</hi> or principall Phiſition, in whoſe power and skill onely the cure lyeth, it is none but God alone, under him in the Miniſteriall worke; both Magiſtrates and Miniſters. Some of theſe are more for outward applications, and ſome for inward; of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſort there are the Magiſtrates, eſpecially the King, or as <hi>Galen</hi> (if my memory doth not faile mee) ſaith of a Phyſition, that <hi>Medicus debet eſſe, tanquam Imperator,</hi> ſo I may ſay on the contrary, that <hi>Imperator debet eſſe tanquam medicus,</hi> a King ought to be like a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian (under him) the ſubordinate Governours for ordinary and particular cures, of known and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſeaſes, the Miniſters they are for inward appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; The Parliament is that great Councell, or Colledge of ſtate Phyſitians, aſſembled under his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to conſider of publike and extraordinary evills, which are not ſo ſafely to be committed to the skill or faith of particular Men, and they are to conſider of all ſorts of diſtempers, whether inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in Church, or State, whether they be againſt our Temporall, or Spirituall good, and ſince both theſe workes are in their hands, and agents are to be fitted to their endes, I deſire it may be ſeriouſly waighed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould not Conſiſt of both Spirituall, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill members, that may be fitted both for the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159507:12"/>and remedy of both ſorts of diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the great and extraordinary doctors of the Common-wealth and Church, of whom under God wee hope for the cure, that the body may againe receive vitall action, freely and without interception from the Soule, and the ſoule yeeld it franckly unto the body. The Medicines, that they are to apply, are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and good Lawes, for <hi>quod Medieamenta morbis id praeſtant jura negotiis,</hi> ſaith the Civill Law.</p>
            <p>So you ſee it is a worke of medicine or healing, and in this reſpect as it requireth in them skill, faithfulnes, courage, freedome from paſſion. So it concerneth you to demeane your ſelves quietly, whether you reckon your ſelves to be patients, as I confeſſe I doe, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as aſſiſtants, or ſtanders by. If patients the very title teacheth you not to be impatient.</p>
            <p>If aſſiſtants, or ſtanders by, you muſt not trouble or interpoſe in the worke, if you can ſay any thing, that may give light unto the Phyſitian, for the more cleare diſcovery of the diſeaſe, doe it in the name of God modeſtly, and peaceably; but doe not preſcribe to the Phiſitians for the Medicine, leaſt if you will needs be pleaſed, wee that I ſay not you, be not perfectly cured; that Phyſitian, that will yeeld to adminiſter eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, that either the patient longs for, or the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by can talke of, ſhall try many experiments, but heale few diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>And give mee leave here to adviſe you, that you be not too earneſt for Empiricall receipts, that have had ſome ſucceſſe in other Bodies, the various cuſtomes, or age, or temper of this, and the neceſſities of thoſe may much alter the caſe, and perhaps though the bodies be like, the diſeaſes are not the ſame, perhaps the ſame
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159507:12"/>ingredientes here in this Climate may have another kind of vertue, either in nature or degree then they have in other; as it is obſerved of Phyſicall ſimples. I pray you leave the Phyſitians to their owne worke, and doe not diſturbe them with clamorous exactions.</p>
            <p>They are not mett as Cooks in a Kitchin, to pleaſe your pallats, but as Phyſitians in <hi>Conclavi medicinali,</hi> to diſpleaſe your diſeaſes, and to heale your body.</p>
            <p>Let them alone then, and trouble them no longer (with I pray you adminiſter this, or that) but leave it to their skill and care: and to the bleſſing of God, and take heed eſpecially you preſcribe not to him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is a worke of reparation of the houſe or Spirituall Temple of God: and therefore as in the building of the Temple, there was no noyſe of axe or hammer to be heard, but all things were to bee done without noyſe or tumult, ſo here in this repaire of the Spirituall Temple all things are to bee done without tumult, or paſſion. God would not have his holy Arke carried upon Beaſts, but by men, which mee thinkes; may intimate thus much unto us, that he will have matters of the Church managed not by paſſions and unruly affections which is the beaſtly part in us, but by calme and quiet reaſon, which is the part which ſtiles us men.</p>
            <p>At leaſt it is not fit for you to trouble your ſelves and them in this kinde, becauſe of your different con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and various intereſt you have in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. That your Conſtitution is different from theirs. If you confeſſe not, the diſtance is ſo much the greater, you will not deny, I am con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ident, but there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees of wiſdome betwixt you. I will not ſay very neere, as much as is betweene the ſenſitive and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159507:13"/>rationall. It is well if you have enough to ſteere you right in your private and mechanicall affaires, which is your proper ſtation, or calling, and you may doe well to conſider, whether you doe well to neglect that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe God hath ſet you about, to meddle with that you have no calling unto. But they are Starres of a greater magnitude, and therefore may move in a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Spheare, and you may be content to receive their influences I hope, it is not in you all to challenge ſo much light unto your ſelves, as to judge of lawes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made, much leſſe to determine and ſet downe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially unto them, what conſtitutions they are to frame.</p>
            <p>And as your conſtitution is very divers, ſo your intereſt is not the ſame with theirs. Their calling and commiſſion, unto which you amongſt others have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, engageth them to the well-doing of the worke ſo far, that they are anſwereable to the great God for all errours and miſpriſions therein, and muſt goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way either with the glory, or the ſhame of it. Your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is to receive the benefit together with them of their happy deſignes, to reape the harveſt of that good ſeed, which they ſhall ſow, to gather the fruit of thoſe wholſome plants, which they ſhall plant in the garden of the Common-wealth, which I wiſh may prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every one of us, as the Garden, or paradiſe of God, yeilding forth unto you, that mortall fruit of the tree of life, and of knowledge, free both from the curſe of the one, or the flaming ſword of the other, to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall comfort of all your ſoules. If this move you not to give over your unquiet motions, give me leave to mind you of the generall concernement, I might ſay of all Chriſtendome, and the world, for I hope this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:159507:13"/>may prove in the event, and diffuſive good of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations to have beene an Oecumenicall Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that may open fountaines of truth, and peace together with holineſſe, unto the whole univerſe, to water, and make fruitfull all the Barren and thirſty places of the world, that like the Sun or Starrs in the Firmament, they may diſperſe the glorious beames of their light into the darkeſt corners of the Earth. But I need not fetch my riſe ſo-farre, the generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of the whole ſtate, and Church of <hi>England,</hi> if you conſider it, as you may and ought to doe, will yeild you reaſonable motives enough to ſit down, and not to take upon you to be moderatours, and beare the ſway according to your humours in thoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, which concerne them all, unleſſe you could ſhew any warrant from the whole, whereby they have deſigned you to become their ſollicitours.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe you are a great and a principall part; but yet you are not the whole body. There are many millions more, that muſt either bee happy, or unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in the ſucceſſe of this Parliament, then are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walles, or ſubburbes of this Citty, whereof you are thought to bee no greater a parte, then you make ſhew off, and you cannot aſſure mee nor yourſelues, that thoſe things that you ſo earneſtly looke for; will bee ſatisfactory to all the reſt. They have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their cauſe to your uote, but to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whom they have made their Vicars and proxies for the managing of this great worke. And as they gave them this power freely, ſo they may juſtly looke that it may bee freely exerciſed by them, unto whom they have ſo committed it, and may well take any force in the leaſt appearance that is offered upon them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159507:14"/>to bee a limitation of their owne freedome. will not this brotherly regard prevaile with you? I truſt at leaſt you are tender of the Parliament, your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions averre it, let your performances confirme it. Conſider therefore in the fourth place, the great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations that theſe proceedings of yours may ſeeme to lay upon them. The Galls of the ſpurrs are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally abated for, in the price and uallue of the horſe The vſe of the whip or the voyce of the rider is in a ſort the reproach of the Palfrey. Frequent Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have their ſecret Accuſations in them, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men take it for a difgrace to bee invited too often to their duties: Eſpecially if there be the leaſt ſhew of violence or force in it, it doth not only tax either the wiſdome or the will or the power of the Agents, which are attended with Ignominy, but it doth alſo rob uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the praiſe by taking away the glory that is in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> freedome of her Performances, and diſcorrageth the work by making it ſeeme ſlaviſh.</p>
            <p>You are wiſe enough to make the application, and I have buſines enough to doe to forbeare it, or if you will have it, make it your ſelves, by giving your ſelves the anſwere vnto theſe few Queſtions.</p>
            <p>Doe you thinke the Parliament wiſe enough to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne and diſcover what is fit to bee done, and to Lay hold vpon the fitte opportunities, which belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every motion to be ſett forward?</p>
            <p>Doe you conceive they are honeſt enough in their wills, to make a fitt and a ſeaſonable purſuit of thoſe good ends which they have before them.</p>
            <p>Doe you think them furniſht with abilities anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the worke in hand, and to bring the meanes &amp; the iſſue together?</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:159507:14"/>
            <p>Doe you know where to mend them in all or any of theſe? I am ſure I doe not, and I thinke not you; why then may they not be truſted with the worke, why can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not they bee lett alone? why doe not you Conceive it better for you to follow your trads &amp; callings which is the buſines which God hath ſett you about, then to trouble your ſelues &amp; others in your vnneceſſary mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings at weſtminſter? I ſay noe more in this point, But I pray you bee tender of the Credit of the Parliament</p>
            <p>Or if not: yet in the fifth place, Let mee adviſe you bee tender of the ſucceſſe it ſelf; the Proverb is I con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe, that many hands make light worke, but it is not all wayes verified in the better ſenſe, ſomtimes the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of agents takes not ſoe much from the burthen &amp; toyle, as from the waight and the ſubſtance of it.</p>
            <p>A buſines may be halfe loſt if wee take not heed in a confuſed Crowd, eſpecilly where the ſkill is not multiplied with the numbers: Too much handling doth vſe to ſoyle the Artifice, and over much medling may aſwell diſturbe the order and frame, as put for ward the Courſe of the motion, and if it move not in order and frame, the ſwifter it goes on, the ſooner it may be ſhaken to peeces, and bury our hopes together in its ruine.</p>
            <p>Take heed I beſeech you, the Fabrique in hand is a peece of great Curioſity, and depends much upon the right diſpoſure of the parts; And therefore not fit for the touch of every raſh and unskilfull hand, untill it be wholly made up and perfected, and then I hope it will be ſo compacted together, that you may ſafely both waigh it, and enjoy it, and will have no need of any mending by your hands. Till then your wiſeſt courſe will be to ſtand a looſe of, and take what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159507:15"/>you can in the view of it at diſtance, but give not your judgement till you ſee it finiſhed; Hee that ſhould ſtand by a Painter, and ſhould ſee him drawing the firſt and ſecond Lineaments of that peece which he meanes to perfect hereafter, and judge of the worke before it be halfe done, would detract much from the Painters skill, and not adde much unto his owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Snſpend your cenſure then, till the workmen give over, and bee not too buſie in tonching, and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it before the coullours be quit dry, leaſt you moyle your ſelves and deface the peece, and ſo lay your owne errours upon the Artificers.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, if all this cannot turne the ſcales, give mee leave in the ſixt and laſt place to preſent unto you one weighty and ſerious conſideration, and to deſire you to be ſeriouſly cautelous, that you doe not ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, what you entend to promote. I know it is your deſire that the healthfull and glorious deſigne in hand, may not onely bee perfected and finiſhed, but that it may bee fixed, and ſetled upon ſo ſtrong a Baſis and foundation that it may not be ſhaken down againe by any ſtormes or tempeſts whatſoever, that the Devill or any inſtruments of his can raiſe againſt it: That thoſe good lawes which ſhall bee now enacted, may bee as a chaine of gold for glory, and excellency, ſo that they may be ſtrong and dureable as yron, able to bind, and keepe in their due order and limits all the moſt extravagant members of this ſtate.</p>
            <p>Now the great Buttreſſe or Foundation upon which the Lawes of England ſtand (If I be not miſtaken) is upon the free conſent of the King and ſubject, in the compoſing and farming of them. And that is indeed the ſtrongeſt mettall to make a chaine of, to bind men
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159507:15"/>withall, that any humane Lawgiver can make choiſe of, ſince it is that ſuits beſt with the nature of man, which is commonly amourous of Libertie, and is apt to take all things with the left hand that ſavour of abridgement or impoſition: And doth alſo prevent them moſt of all excuſes or quarrells againſt the lawes, for ſince it doth in a ſort make them all (for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part in policy) as well parties and agents in the making of the yoke, as paſſive in the bearing of it, we are ſo much the more deprived of all plea and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt it, untill it bee taken off, or abrogated by the like power and upon the ſame termes.</p>
            <p>It is our generall inclination, that we had rather be taken to yeeld, than to be overcome, for though they both take up at one Inne many times, yet the former is thought to bee the fairer way: whatſoever our owne wills have not a hand in the paſſing, wee uſually account our ſelves eyther rob'd or cheated of; But that which is given away, is thought as good very neere as a poſſeſſion, and a voluntary bondage better then a forced freedome, (if I may ſo ſpeake) yea wee take our ſelves to bee all a kind of Kings, as long as wee under a voluntary ſubjection. And indeede ſuch kind of Lawes are of a larger juriſdiction than others that put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on with force &amp; violence, and are received with reluctancy of the people, ſince they lay hold upon the whole man in a ſort, and engage the will it ſelfe, which is moſt in tollerant of captivity-and the moſt unſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able objectour againſt ſuch kind of obligations; And as their extent is more Large, ſo their force more ſtrong too, ſince to the reaſon of the law and power of the Lawgiver, they carry alſo the conſent of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which three makes up that three fold cord which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:159507:16"/>is not eaſily broken, whereby Laws are bound up into a ſolid body, and ſecured from the ſhocke of refracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines or oppoſition.</p>
            <p>The reaſon or wiſedom of the Law is I confeſſe, the moſt reaſonable engagement, and the neceſſity of any other I conceive to be the fruit of corruption, but wee muſt bee conſidered and provided for as wee are, and that is (I doubt) for the moſt part conſiſting, more of will then Iudgement: So few there are amongſt us I fearc, that have underſtanding enough to bee convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and therefore as the caſe ſtands for the generall, hee doth too litle for the inforcement of a rule, that makes it bright and cleare, For the eye of the ſoule, unleſſe he add ſome ſpring or motion to ſway the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving part, which is the will which proues of two ſullen a temper many times to embrace that light which is offered though it be never ſo cleare, and good. There is a <hi>medea</hi> in us whch bewitcheth us to a <hi>video meliora proboque, deteriora ſequor.</hi> So that there muſt be ſtrength in a Law, as well as light and reaſon, to ſway the will, as well as to convince the judgement.</p>
            <p>And the will or motive part of man ſhewes it ſelfe in two things, in inclinetion, and action. The power of the Lawgiver may doe ſomething upon the Latter to reſtraine or agritate our performances, but it hath lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to do with the former, the inclination, &amp; if that bee not ſubdued in ſome reaſonable ſort the obedience in acction will be neither conſtant not ſincere, but accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with murmurrs and complaints, with Evaſions and imputations both upon the Law and Lawgivers, as tyrannicall and oppreſſive; But where the conſent of thoſe that are to be ſubject goes along with the reſt, and hath a competent ſhare in the making of Lawes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159507:16"/>there the Iudgement and outward actions are bound up together with the in lination, and the yoke is made in a ſort lonely &amp; eaſie, being lined as it were with the conſent of the ſubjects, which keepes it from galling, and them from wearineſſe and complaining. And there fore that government where this conſent is wanting, muſt either have a weake or ſlaviſh people to deale with, or it may prove but wavering and of no long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, which maketh me beleeve that the governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England</hi> both in this and other reſpects, if it be kept within its moderate limits, is the beſt governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the world.</p>
            <p>A maine thing therefore for the conſolidating and eſtabliſhing of Lawes is the free and generall conſent of the people, in making of them: And this conſent is of two ſorts, either perſonall or numerall, whetein all have their particular and expreſſe votes, or by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and proxey, where the conſents of the whole are made over unto ſome that are repreſentative of all the reſt who ſubmit both their Iudgements and their wills unto them, vvhich is moſt neceſſary in great &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous bodies, both for the avoiding of Tumult and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teny, which is too ordinarily incident unto great mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and for the ſupply of that want of judgement which is in the many, which would hardly either direct them to the beſt, or admit of agreement in that which were tollerable.</p>
            <p>And alſo for aprevention of a diſſolution of trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which muſt neceſſarily follow, if every particular member ſhould leave his ordinary function, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. and betake himſelfe to the making of Lawes: which would be alſo the diſſolution of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and were to deſtroy the body, for the cure of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:159507:17"/>the diſeaſes of it. And indeed it is but to yelld unto meere neceſſities, and impoſſiblities, (Tyrants that we muſt all live under) which forbid any faiſible orderly concurrence of ſo many into one Councell or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claue. ſince no place would be either bigge enough to receive them, neither would their immenſity ſuffer them to draw neere enough together, to Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Councels, and advices, but one part muſt needs be a ſtranger unto the other, Nor would their number or multitude admit of any fit courſe or time, for the computation or comparing of their votes: for theſe, and perhaps ſome other reaſons, which for the preſent I think not of, it is moſt neceſſary, &amp; unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that the innumerable multitude of the Subjects of a Kingdome, ſhould by ellection of their Proxies, and reſpective attorneys be reduced into a competent and aſſemlable all company of thoſe, which are of the wiſer, and more excellent conſtitution, who are to act for all the reſt, and in their name, and power to give their voyces either with, or againſt thoſe conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are to be binding to the whole body. And here I conceive is the very reaſonable, and even natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall foundation of a Parliament, which is that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Quinteſſentiall Body, as I may ſo ſpeake, in whom the whole State or Common-wealth doth both judge, and conſent either to approve or diſapprove of thoſe thinges which ſhall be propoſed, The members whereof I conceive to bee of two ſorts, ſome ſetled and apointed in their particuler condiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the fundamentals lawes of this kingdome, which may ſeeme to bee a kinde of originall ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clection, others occaſionally choſen by the uotes of the people whoſe electiue uoyces fortified by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:159507:17"/>Kings writ or commiſſion, deſignes them for their <hi>legis-latiue,</hi> and Parlamentary power. In this body there are uertually contained al the conſiderable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Common-wealth eyther in perſon, or by their ioynt and ſeuerali procuratours and atrurnyes: And as their acts are in account the Acts of the whole State, ſo their freedom is in a manner the freedome of the whole, and any uiolence which may be deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue unto their free proceedings is equally operatiue as may ſeeme for the diſſen forceing of their lawes, or at leaſt to give a hint unto thoſe that have a deſire to exept againſt them, as if it had beene offered unto the great body of the Common-wealth it ſelfe, neyther skills it much, (I conceave) whether this uiolence (bee it in truth, or in appearance) proceed from an externall or forraigne power, or from an unauthenticall part of the ſame body, for the generall conſent or freedom ſeemes abated, not onely when they are ſurprized and awed by forraigne forces or terrour, but when any part doth give a ſemblance of ſwaying and overpowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the reſt, or to draw and exact from them that which is done by clamour or tumult, eſpecially when that part have deveſted themſelves of their power and uotes, by tranſlating them upon that repreſentative body. And ſuch is the caſe with you and the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament. Therefore if you ſhould but by the ſhew of terrour and uiolence (which your irregular concourſe, and tumults may ſavour off) detract any thing but in appearance from their freedome in their agitation and concluſion of thoſe buſineſſes they have in hand: Take heede you doe not endanger an abatement of the eſtimate or ualue of thoſe lawes which they ſhall make, and that you prepare not too much roome for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:159507:18"/>thoſe that ſhall diſlike them hereafter, to pretend that they were made in terrour and tumult, and rather by the clamour af a multitude, than by the uotes and deliberate judgements of thoſe to whom the King and kingdome had committed the worke, and ſo by your too much keeneſſe in urging and preſſing upon the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, you take not off the edge and efficacy of their conſtitutions. Since thoſe decrees that have too much of force in the making, prove many times to have too litle in the binding.</p>
            <p>Let mee intreat you therefore my brethren as you love the peace of the Church, and deſire the happy end may be attained, unto which the great Counſell of the Kingdome is now directed, and that it may proue a ſolid and eſtabliſhed worke, that you will weigh theſe reaſons, with an impartiall minde, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of all ſelfe-love and preiudice and that you will now at length deſiſt and ſit downe, and expect with patience the deſired ſucceſſe, let it be yoar ſtuddy to live uprightly and honeſtly in your trades and callings, and to keepe your ſelves within your limits, and to the conſcionable exerciſe of your proper imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and not to intrude into that you underſtand not: If you will needs be active in reformation, let it be in the reformation of your ſelves. Call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in your owne hearts and aſſemble all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of your ſoules in the covrt of your owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to diſcover and redreſſe thoſe grievances that are there, which lye toward the ruine of that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, which will be the beſt way, that I know for you to take, to ſet forward the publike reformation, en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct lawes in your owne hearts againſt your owne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteouſnes; your oppreſſions, your deceitfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:159507:18"/>dealings in your trades, againſt your unquiet and diſtempered affections, againſt your ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pride and factions, inclinations, execute judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon thoſe firebrands there, which are ever contriving a deviſion and ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your God and you, and between you and one another, and adorne your felves with a meeke and quiet ſpirit, which in the ſight of God is of great price, ſo ſhall you bee a great meanes to cauſe God to divert his judgements from us, and to reſtore his favorable countenance towards us againe, and to ſend his bleſſing upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the whole State to the redreſſe of thoſe evills under which we labour and to the procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and eſtabliſhment of that good which may be to the reſetling of this tottering Church and State in that condition which ſhall bee beſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto him, &amp; moſt comfortable unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, delivering us both from ſuperſtition and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, garding us both from Tyranny and Anarchy protecting us both from oppreſſion and rebellion, freeing us both from heriſie and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that wee may bee a glorious Church unto himſelfe, and an imitable example both of peace, truth &amp; holines to the whole world: That a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation may be laid here of a great converſation of the whole world unto Chriſt of the calling home of the Iews, of the convertion of all turkes &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and all Antichriſtian and wicked hereticks, to the aboliſhment of the Tyranny and uſupation of that man of ſinne, the Romiſh wolfe, and to the wiſhed reconcilement of the Proteſtant Churches and all others in one and the ſame ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:159507:19"/>and ſubſtantiall truth, however any of them may differ in outward formes or ceremonies. God of his mercy grant this unto us, and make you to deſire nothing but what is conducing hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and give you grace to perſue it peaceably and chriſtianly, yeelding to the neceſſity of a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall and orderly proceeding, and not running out of one extreame into another, leaſt the evills be rather changed then remedred. In ſuch defines the Lord grant you a gracious hearing, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you with a deſired bleſſing, to the confuſion of his enemies, and the promotion and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpel and Kingdome of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the ſame God bleſſe, guide, and protect the Kings Majeſtie, and the high and honorable aſſembly of Parliament, a proceeding free from all deviſion and paſſion with comptiame and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondancy, they may conclude in that, not which you not I, or any other may fancy or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, but in that which is agreeable to the will, and conducing to the glory or God, thoug never ſo contrary to your deſires and to the reformation of all evills in the Church and ſtate, and the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of peacle and truth amongſt us, Amen.</p>
            <p>But alas I doubt the prime fountaine of their diſtemper, is notiin you altogether, I remember I have read a ſaying to this purpoſe. That <hi>popluus eſt tanquam mare, quod exſequietam et tanquillum ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per manet nullis fluctitie agitatur niſi cum ab Aeolis concitatur ſurit.</hi> That the people are like unto the ſea, which of it ſelfe is quiet and calme, not toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with waves and ſurges when it is troubled, and agitated with winds. There are therefore it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:159507:19"/>may be doubted ſome <hi>Aeoli</hi> amongſt you, ſome vu ruly; and ſwelling ſpirits that are the <hi>boutefeux,</hi> and ſhirrers up of thoſe tempeſtuous motions which are among you, I dare not accuſe any; but who ever they be, let me tell them that I doubt it will be found a worke that will receive but an uncomfortable recompence from the God of peace, to kindle the fire of tumult and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the Church, if Vriah met with a breath from the Lord, for laying a raſh hand upon the Arke, to keepe it from falling, when it was ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, what a breach thinke you may they expect, that by their timorous attempts upon it, doe as much as in them lyeth, ſhiver into peeces that holy arke of the Lords houſe, looke but upon the <hi>Guerdon</hi> of murmurers, and factioniſts in this world; in the fixteenth of the Booke of <hi>Numb.</hi> And it may light you to a ſhrewd gueſt what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they are like to have in the world to come; I am loath to ſuppect any, but give me leave to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh all, <hi>Et capuit qui capere poteſt,</hi> and to put you in mind how diſproportioned ſuch wiſedom is unto that wiſedome which commeth from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, which the Apoſtle telleth you, not I, (and I hope he may yet paſſe for anthenticall) that it is firſt pure then peaceable, Gentle, eaſie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, full of mercy, and good fruits without judging and without hypocriſie; and before at the thirteen verſe of the ſame Chapter, <hi>who is a wiſe man, and endued with knowledge among you, let him ſhew by a good converfation, his workes in meekeueſſe and wiſedome;</hi> And on the contrary. But
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:159507:20"/>if yee have bitter envying, and ſtriſe in your hearts, rejoyce not, neither be liers againſt the truth, this wifed once deſendeth not from above, but is earrhly; ſenſuall, diveliſh; For where envy, and ſtrine is; there is ſedition and all manner of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill workes, ſurely if Saint <hi>Iames</hi> be canonicall Scripture (as I hope that will be none of our new doubts) then this is a orthodox Doctrine, and if this be orthodox doctrine, the praetife of ſome of you is but an hetrodox practiſe, the I ordes are ſo cleare, they neede no great comintary, you ſee heere the plaine characters, of heavenly and dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh wifedome ſet downe by their true and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite properties in the: name of God, unmaske your ſelves, and looke upon your ſelves in this glaſſe, and I am perſwaded you will not all be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured on your owne features, you will I hope be out of love than with the deformity of tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous proſeedings.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially my Brethren of the miniſtry, I beſeech you by all thoſe great bonds of obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation that you owe vnto <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the prince of peace, That as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be Miniſters of peace, and as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of (peace ſo your would by all meanes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fible both by doctrine &amp; example <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I beſeech you all Vainglory &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of populatity; &amp; put on the ſpirit of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s &amp; ſincerity let your tongues be lick the Tongue of the wiſe which is health, to like whole againe (as I may ſo ſpeake) the ſores and breaches of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:159507:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; not like the tongue of the wicked which is as words and ſpeares: to pierce and vulnerate the myſticall body of Chriſt, and to make brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in that building which he hath Cemented to gether with his owne moſt precious bloud: oh ſtifle I beſeech you, that bitter proverbe, that it may be anathematized fio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongeſt vs that <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne malum a ſacerdotique.</hi> But alas why do I ſpeake thus vnto you, I beſeech you pardon me; I doe willingly acknowledge, the miniſtry of London to be the Glory of the Church of Eugland, but yet I feare there may be ſome meteors, amongſt thoſe glorious ſtares, if there be, than this is theyrs. And I intreat them to conſider of it with a meeke and a chriſtian heart, and to waigh it well, whether that truth laſteth not longeſt and ſpeedeth not beſt, that is brought in &amp; fomented by a peaceable mind, &amp; ſo I committ you al unto God, and to the power of his grace, beſeeching his gloriours Majeſty that he will give us al hearts to endeavor the making up of thoſe miſerable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions that are amongſt us, that mercy and truth may meete to together, and righteouſneſſe and peace may kiſſe each other: that he will be pleaſed to take pitty upon our poore diſtreſſed Churches, that they bee not conſumed in the flames of their owne diſcords to the glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing of the adverſaries of the Lord, that once more we may ſerve him with united hearts, and that peace may be within our walles, and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe within our palaces: none but thou on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly canſt doe it O Lord, helpe us O Lord our God,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:159507:21"/>for vaine is the helpe of man; And ſo the God of peac ewhich brought againe from the dead the Lord Ieſus, the great ſhepehard of the ſheepe make you perfect, ſtrengthen and ſtabliſh you and us all, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:159507:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
